Guide to the Padgett Powell Papers, 1972-2015 RL.01042
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Padgett Powell papers
1972-2018
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Powell, Padgett
RL.01042
12 Linear Feet
Author and professor at the University of Florida. Published works include Edisto, A Woman Named Drown, Typical, Mrs. Hollingsworth's Men, and The Interrogative Mood: A Novel?. Collection includes writings and drafts of Powell's early novels, including Edisto and A Woman Named Drown, as well as essays, short stories, and articles for popular magazines and literary anthologies. Some of these appear in Typical, a collection of Powell's short stories. The collection also includes correspondence, publishing contracts, reviews, interviews, and travel files, many relating to the publication of Edisto.
9000 Items; 34 boxes
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted. During Powell's lifetime, access to all correspondence and business records (now held in the Correspondence and Professional Materials Series) require prior written permission from him. Commercial use of any materials requires prior approval from Powell or his agent.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Padgett Powell Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1993, 2012, and 2015.
Biographical Note
Padgett Powell is an American author who teaches writing at the University of Florida. His first novel, Edisto, was published in 1984 to wide acclaim, and was nominated for the American Book Award. He has since published several more books, including A Woman Named Drown (1987), Typical (1991), Edisto Revisited (1996), Aliens of Affection (1998), Mrs. Hollingsworth's Men (2000), The Interrogative Mood: A Novel? (2009), and You and I (2011).
Collection Overview
The Padgett Powell Papers contains 4 series: Writings, Professional Materials, Correspondence, and Oversize Materials. The majority of the collection lies in the Writings Series, which includes drafts and publishing materials from Powell's books. The Writings Series also has a large run of Powell's "General Writings," which includes essays and articles for various publications, travel pieces, short stories (some of which later appeared in published books), and other drafts. These files may include multiple versions of the text, as well as correspondence with the piece's publisher.
Additional correspondence can be found in the Correspondence Series, which includes Powell's communications with editors, publishers, awards committees, and various literary figures. This series has been arranged to reflect Powell's initial arrangement: general and literary correspondence has been filed first, followed by an alphabetized subject and name file. Dates are included when known.
The collection's Professional Materials include both travel files, interview files, and some of Powell's academic work and records from his student days at the College of Charleston and at the University of Houston. The Oversize Materials series includes miscellaneous objects, usually related to publicizing or advertising Powell's readings or books.
American literature -- 20th century; Authors, American -- 20th century; College teachers as authors; Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence; University of Florida -- Faculty; Powell, Padgett -- Typical; Powell, Padgett -- Edisto; Powell, Padgett -- A Woman Named Drown
- Writings, 1983-2015
  Scope and Contents note
  The majority of the collection lies in the Writings Series, which includes drafts, edits, and publishing materials from Powell's books. The Writings Series also has a large run of Powell's "General Writings," which includes essays and articles for various publications, travel pieces, short stories (some of which later appeared in Typical), and other drafts. These files may include multiple versions of the text, as well as correspondence with the piece's publisher.
  - Edisto
    Materials relating to Edisto include early drafts of the book; correspondence and drafts from its excerption in The New Yorker; several revised galleys and proofs; "scraps" and "dead matter" leftover from the book's publication; foreign edition contracts; reviews; and screenplay versions of the text.
    - Masters' Thesis, University of Houston, December 1982 (Box 1)
    - Early drafts with revisions, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Pat Strachan working manuscript and galleys (Box 1)
    - Longhand drafts, undated, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Draft, undated (Box 2)
    - "Scraps" of draft (Box 2)
    - Preface draft (Box 2)
    - Farrar Straus and Giroux (FS&G) contract, 1983 (Box 2)
    - New Yorker proofs, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
    - New Yorker proofs, 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - New Yorker original manuscript (Box 3)
    - New Yorker published excerpt, 1983 (Box 3)
    - Page proofs (Box 3)
    - "Dead matter" (Box 3)
    - 3 chapters, longhand draft (Box 3)
    - Correspondence with FS&G, 1984 (Box 3)
    - Advertisements (Box 3)
    - Book of the Month Club (Box 3)
    - Braille edition (Box 3)
    - Finnish edition (Box 3)
    - French edition (Box 4)
    - German edition (Box 4)
    - Hebrew edition (Box 4)
    - Italian edition (Box 4)
    - Japan edition (Box 4)
    - Paperback (Owl) edition (Box 4)
    - Spanish edition (Box 4)
    - Swedish edition (Box 4)
    - UK edition (Box 4)
    - Memorandum of agreement with Profile Books Ltd (UK edition), 2011 Jan. 26 (Box 34)
    - Fan mail, 1983-1985 (Box 4)
    - Academic reviews (Box 4)
    - Reviews and press, 3 folders (Box 4)
    - Published reviews and articles, 1984-1985 (Box 4)
    - MGM/UA, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Screenplay draft (Box 5)
    - Screenplay, Lonner, David, 1985-1992 (Box 5)
    - Clippings re: film (Box 5)
    - Sundance, 1986 (Box 5)
    - MacGill's Literary Annual, 1985 (Box 5)
    - Cover designs, undated (Box 34)
  - A Woman Named Drown
    Materials from A Woman Named Drown include drafts and revisions, including a series labeled by Powell as A-S; "dead matter" and other excerpts from the text; foreign edition correspondence; and reviews and fan mail.
    - Drafts and manuscripts, undated, 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Drafts, undated, and correspondence, 1986 (Box 6)
    - Early drafts, 1986 (Box 6)
    - "Dead matter" (Box 6)
    - Final longhand draft (Box 6)
    - Drafts, A-S, 1986, 5 folders (Box 6)
    - Draft with text notes and edits (Box 6)
    - Draft excerpts (Box 7)
    - Draft (Box 7)
    - Reading copy draft (Box 7)
    - Cover, cat., flap, etc. (Box 7)
    - Blurb, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Holt (paperback) edition (Box 7)
    - French edition (Box 7)
    - German edition (Box 7)
    - Portuguese editions (Drown and Edisto) (Box 7)
    - Swedish edition (Box 7)
    - Fan mail, 1987 (Box 7)
    - Reviews (2 folders) (Box 7)
  - Typical
    Materials relating to the publication of Typical, including various drafts of different stories, proofs and edits, reviews, and some fan mail. There are other versions of stories appearing in Typical in the General Writings subseries, described below.
    - Drafts of stories (Box 8)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Elliot and Cleveland draft (Box 8)
    - Collection drafts (Box 8)
    - "Dead matter," 1992 (Box 8)
    - Proofs with edits, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Gallery proofs with edits, February 1992, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - Galley proofs with edits (legal size) (Box 10)
    - Master pages with edits (legal size) (Box 10)
    - Galleys and edits (legal size) (Box 10)
    - Reviews, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Fan mail (Box 11)
    - German edition (Box 11)
    - Reprints-BOMB/USIS (Box 11)
  - The Interrogative Mood: A Novel?
    This subseries includes only copyedited drafts and proofs from the publication of The Interrogative Mood: A Novel?.
    - 2008 version (Box 11)
    - Early draft with edits (Box 11)
    - Master: first pass, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Master: first pass (Box 12)
    - Author's second pass, 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Copyedited draft (Box 12)
    - Draft, 2007-2008 (Box 22)
    - Draft (sans 1st page) and proof, 2008-2009 (Box 34)
      Scope and Contents
      3 folders
    - Book Tour, 2009 (Box 22)
    - New Yorker Cut, undated (Box 22)
    - Profile Paper, undated (Box 22)
    - Publicity/reviews, 2009-2012 (Box 34)
      Includes German, Spanish, French, and Italian. 3 boxes
  - You and Me, 2
    - Manifesto/You and Me, undated (Box 23)
    - Drafts, 2004 and undated (Box 23)
    - Review Draft, 2011 Dec 23 (Box 23)
    - Proof, UK edition, 2011 May 8 (Box 34)
    - Incomplete proof, paperback edition, 2013 Mar. 15 (Box 34)
    - Jacket designs, undated (Box 34)
    - Publicity/reviews, 2011-2012 (Box 34)
  - Edisto Revisited, 3
    - Draft, 1994 Nov 9 (Box 23)
    - Review Draft, 1st Pass, 1995 Oct 30 (Box 23)
    - Draft, undated; 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Draft 2, undated (Box 23)
    - Draft 3, undated (Box 24)
    - Partial Draft, 1995 June 12 (Box 24)
    - Working Draft, undated (Box 24)
    - Working Draft A, undated (Box 24)
    - Working Draft B, undated (Box 24)
    - Working Draft C, undated (Box 24)
    - 2nd Draft, Bill's Copy, undated (Box 24)
    - Edits from Pat Strachan (Houghton Mifflin), 2002 and undated (Box 25)
    - Original Edisto Revisited Manuscript, 1996 Dec 16 (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous Draft Pages, undated (Box 25)
    - Publicity/reviews, 1996-1998 (Box 34)
    - Correspondence and commentary from Harry Rowohlt, 1996-1997 (Box 34)
    - Correspondence, 1996-1999 (Box 34)
    - Fan mail, 1996 (Box 34)
  - Mrs. Hollingsworth's Men, 4
    - Draft with Edits from Pat Strachan, undated (Box 25)
    - Revised Version of pages 2-33, 2000 Feb 11 (Box 25)
    - Draft, 2000 Apr 6 (Box 25)
    - Copy-edited Manuscript, 2000 Mar (Box 25)
    - Final Manuscript, 2001 July 25 (Box 26)
    - Master/Proofer Set, 2000 May 2 (Box 26)
    - Author's Marked Set, 2000 May 2 (Box 26)
    - Draft, undated (Box 26)
    - Promotional Material, undated (Box 26)
    - Book Tour, 2000 (Box 26)
    - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 26)
    - Manuscript Fragment, 2000 Apr 26 (Box 26)
    - Draft, 2000 May 2 (Box 27)
    - Marked Copy, undated (Box 27)
    - Draft, undated; 2 folders (Box 27)
    - Publicity/reviews, 2000 (Box 34)
  - Hologram, 5
    - Manuscript Copy, undated (Box 27)
    - First Edit (includes original folder with edits), undated (Box 28)
    - 2nd Edit (?), undated (Box 28)
    - Blount 1 with edits and notes, 1996 and undated (Box 28)
    - Blount 2, undated (Box 28)
    - Draft with Edits, undated (Box 28)
    - Correspondence and Miscellaneous Documents, 1999-2000 (Box 28)
  - Aliens of Affection, 6
    - Draft, undated (Box 29)
    - Early Copy of Edited Manuscript, undated (Box 29)
    - Various Proofs and Edits, 1997 and undated (Box 29)
    - Miscellaneous Draft Fragments, undated (Box 29)
    - Page Proofs (includes correspondence and notes), 1997 June (Box 30)
    - Correspondence and Edits from Pat Strachan, 1996-1997 (Box 30)
    - Draft Fragments with Edits, undated; 2 folders (Box 30)
    - Early Copy-edited Manuscript, undated (Box 31)
    - Page Proofs with Edits (1st Pass), 1997 June 6 (Box 31)
    - Page Proofs with Edits, 1997 June 6 (Box 31)
    - Cover/jacket design, 1997 (Box 34)
    - Publicity/reviews, 1997-1998 (Box 34)
      Includes German.
  - Cries for Help, Various, 8
    - Drafts with File Lists, 2001-2002 (Box 32)
    - Various story drafts, undated (Box 32)
    - Edited manuscript, 2014 Dec.; 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Corrected manuscript, photocopy, undated (Box 33)
    - Copyedited manuscript with Powell's responses, 2015; 2 folders (Box 33)
    - Bound galley (advance reading copy) and final published copy, 2015 (Box 33)
    - Complete draft, 2007 (Box 34)
      2 folders
  - General Writings (Box 12)
    The General Writings subseries includes drafts of articles, essays, short stories, and other writings by Powell for a wide variety of audiences, including newspapers, popular magazines, and anthologies. Some of these files include early drafts; others include published versions and accompanying correspondence between Powell and the publisher. Some writings are filed by publisher rather than by title; these distinctions were originally made by Powell and have been maintained during archival processing. Also included in this subseries are versions of short stories that later appeared in Typical, Powell's own collection of short stories.
    - A Commencement Speech, undated (Box 32)
    - The Allure of Southern Women, GQ (Box 12)
    - Anthology appearances, 1990-1992 (Box 12)
    - Atlanta Constitution Weekly (Box 12)
    - Barthleme tribute (Box 13)
    - Bedtime, undated (Box 32)
    - Biltmore, New York Times, 1991, 3 folders (Box 13)
    - Book reviews (Box 13)
    - Breakdown, undated (Box 32)
    - Bullies, undated (Box 32)
    - Change of Life, undated (Box 32)
    - The Cork, undated (Box 32)
    - Dizzy, undated (Box 32)
    - Dogs are Coming, undated (Box 32)
    - Dusk, undated (Box 32)
    - Fear and Infinitude (Box 13)
    - Fishing in the Modern World (Box 13)
    - Five Stories and a Piece, 2012 June 21 (Box 32)
    - Five Stories and a Piece, draft with edits, 2012 Jul. 25 (Box 34)
    - Flood (Box 13)
    - Frog and Spode (Box 13)
    - Genie, undated (Box 32)
    - Gift, undated (Box 32)
    - Grading the Old Man (Box 13)
    - Grinace (Box 13)
    - Hard Candy, undated (Box 32)
    - High Trash (Box 13)
    - Hitting Back (Box 13)
    - Hitting Back, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Home and Garden, Dec. 1991 (Box 14)
    - Horses, undated (Box 32)
    - Humpy, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - The Imperative Mood (includes edits, page proofs, and extract), 2012 (Box 32)
    - Joplin and Dickens, 2002 July 12, 2004 Apr 28 (Box 32)
    - Kansas (Box 14)
    - Kills Twice and His Brother, undated (Box 32)
    - Lebove and Son (Box 14)
    - Letter From a Dogfighter's Aunt, Deceased (Box 14)
    - Love, undated (Box 32)
    - Many a One, undated (Box 32)
    - Matter of Time, undated (Box 32)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 32)
    - Modern Italian (Box 14)
    - Mr. and Mrs. Elliot and Cleveland (Box 14)
    - Mr. Irony (Box 14)
    - Mr. Irony, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Mr. Nefarious (Box 15)
    - My Presidential Candidacy, undated (Box 32)
    - New Orleans, New York Times, 1992 (Box 15)
    - New York Times Book Review, 1985 (Box 15)
    - Noble Soldier, undated (Box 32)
    - Nougat, undated (Box 32)
    - On the Range, undated (Box 32)
    - Perhaps South America, undated (Box 32)
    - Sermon, undated (Box 32)
    - Sisters, undated (Box 32)
    - Solitude, undated (Box 32)
    - South Carolina/Mr. Desultory (Box 15)
    - Southern Living 25th Anniversary (Box 15)
    - Spy, undated (Box 32)
    - Steel, undated (Box 32)
    - Territory, undated (Box 32)
    - Thompson, Sandra; St. Pete (Box 15)
    - Ted Turner (Box 15)
    - Tod, undated (Box 32)
    - Typical (Box 15)
    - USA Today, 1985 (Box 15)
    - Wayne II and III (Box 15)
    - Wheat Tour (Box 15)
    - Winnowing of Mrs. Schuping (Box 15)
    - Winnowing of Mrs. Schuping (Box 16)
    - Untitled or loose drafts, 1970s, 4 folders (Box 16)
    - Untitled, undated (Box 32)
    - Wearing a Meat Shirt and Killing a Snake, undated (Box 32)
    - "Scraps and scrappy letters" (Box 16)
    - Blues (Box 16)
    - Introductions (Box 16)
    - "Juvenilia" (Box 16)
    - Publisher Promotional Materials (Edisto Revisited and Aliens of Affection), 1996-1997 (Box 31)
    - Manifesto, draft with edits, 2007-2009 (Box 34)
  - Writings by Others
    - Darling, by William Tester, December 1990 (Box 20)
    - Darling, by William Tester, December 1990 (Box 21)
    - Show Me the Way To Go Home, by Simmons Jones, 1991 (Box 21)
- Professional Materials, 1972-1993; 4 boxes
  The collection's Professional Materials include both travel files, interview files, and some of Powell's academic work and records from his student days at the College of Charleston and at the University of Houston.
  Access Restrictions
  During Powell's lifetime, access to the Professional Materials Series requires prior written permission from him.
  - Travel files, 1984-1989 (Box 16)
  - Travel files, 1989-1993 (Box 17)
  - Interviews, 1985-1987, 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Interviews, 1986-1993 (Box 18)
  - College of Charleston Moulin Rouge issues, 1972 (Box 18)
  - Academic records (Box 18)
  - University of Houston work, 1981-1982 (Box 18)
  - Clippings about Powell, 1980s (Box 21)
  - Magazines with published articles or works, 1984-1992, 4 folders (Box 21)
- Correspondence, 1983-1993; 3 boxes
  Additional correspondence can be found in the Correspondence Series, which includes Powell's communications with editors, publishers, awards committees, and various literary figures. This series has been arranged to reflect Powell's initial arrangement: general and literary correspondence has been filed first, followed by an alphabetized subject and name file. Dates are included when known.
  During Powell's lifetime, access to the Correspondence Series requires prior written permission from him.
  - General, 1983-1985, 2 folders (Box 18)
  - Literary, 1985-1987, 3 folders (Box 18)
  - Literary, 1988-1992, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - AAIAL Rome Fellowship, 1986-1987 (Box 19)
  - American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1987 (Box 19)
  - American Book Awards, 1984 (Box 19)
  - Anthologies/reprints (Box 19)
  - Author's Guild, 1980s (Box 19)
  - Awards (Box 19)
  - Ballet Met, 1988 (Box 19)
  - Bellow, Saul, 1992-1993 (Box 19)
  - Booksellers, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Buckley catalog, 1984 (Box 19)
  - Dunaway, Lynch - film, 1988 (Box 19)
  - Esquire, 1985-1986 (Box 19)
  - Fan mail, 1985 (Box 19)
  - FS&G, 1985-1991, 3 folders (Box 19)
  - Fulbright/Walsh (Box 19)
  - Gambone, Philip, 1985 (Box 19)
  - Guggenheim (Box 19)
  - Harper's, 1989-1990 (Box 19)
  - Henry Holt & Co., 1997-1999 (Box 34)
  - Hope, Jonathan, 2011 (Box 34)
  - ICM and Lynn Nesbit, 1982-1986, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Janklow and Nesbit Associates, 1989-1990 (Box 20)
  - Merchant, Larry (Box 20)
  - Murphy, Daniel, 1992 (Box 20)
  - Nan, undated (Box 20)
  - NEA (Box 20)
  - New Yorker, 1980-1991 (Box 20)
  - Poulouse, Pamela (Box 20)
  - Professorship applications, 1985-1989 (Box 20)
  - Rogers, Bill, 1985 (Box 20)
  - Rolling Stone, 1989 (Box 20)
  - Roman dispatches, 1988 (Box 20)
  - Small, Adrienne, 1992 (Box 20)
  - Soho Square, 1991 (Box 20)
  - Sonneberg, Ben, 1989-1991 (Box 20)
  - Williams, George (Box 20)
  - Wills, 1991 (Box 20)
  - World Authors, 1993 (Box 20)
- Oversize Materials, 1 box and 1 folder
  Oversize material advertising Powell's works, including Edisto and other books.
  - Miscellaneous oversize materials (Box 9)
  - Miscellaneous oversize materials (Oversize-folder 1)